Finding Aid for Robert E. Nederlander Papers, 1969-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert E. Nederlander Papers 1969-1984
Nederlander, Robert E., 1933-
5 linear feet
91427 Aa 2
Businessman from Detroit, Michigan and New York City; regent of the University of Michigan, 1969-1984. Topical files and correspondence relating to his service as regent; subjects include regental reaction to the Black Action Movement in 1970, and the debate over the proposed divestiture of the university's financial interests in South Africa, 1977-1979.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Nederlander (donor no. 7823 ) and came to the library in June 1990.
The collection is open to research.
Robert E. Nederlander was born in Detroit on April 10, 1933. He attended the University of Michigan, receiving his B.A. in 1955 and his J.D. in 1958. He was admitted to the Michigan bar in 1958, and has practiced law in Detroit since that time. He has also served as president of Nederlander Worldwide, Inc. and as executive vice president of the Nederlander Theatrical Corporation. In 1969, Nederlander was elected to the University of Michigan Board of Regents. He served as a regent until 1984, and was known for his liberal position on many university issues.
The collection consists of files pertaining to Robert Nederlander's service on the University of Michigan Board of Regents from 1969 to 1984. It does not include materials relating to any of his other activities. The collection is arranged in two series: Topical Files and Board of Regents Correspondence.
Subjects:
Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); Disinvestment--South Africa.; Nederlander, Robert E., 1933-; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1971-1980.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1981-1990.
- Topical Files 1969-1981
  The Topical Files are arranged alphabetically and include correspondence, memos, and other materials. These files cover such subjects as the Black Action Movement activities of 1970, DNA research, divestiture of South African-related stock, Law School fundraising, student discipline, and open meetings of the Board of Regents.
  - Admission policies 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Afro-American living quarters 1972 (Box 1)
  - Barbour-Waterman Gymnasium 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Black Action Movement 1970
    - General (Box 1)
    - Correspondence re: BAM strike (Box 1)
    - News clippings (Box 1)
  - Black student demands 1970 (Box 1)
  - Black student enrollment 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Board in Control of Medical Center 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Board of Visitors for East Asian Studies 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Bonds, University of Michigan 1977 (Box 1)
  - Budget 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws, University of Michigan 1970 (Box 1)
  - Campaign Reform Act 1977 (Box 1)
  - Classified research 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Conflict of interest 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Court cases 1969-1973 (Box 1)
  - Discrimination policy 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - DNA research 1976-1977, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Federal government clearance 1969 (Box 1)
  - Geography department, discontinuance 1981 (Box 1)
  - Housing lottery 1975 (Box 1)
  - Housing policy, married students 1969 (Box 1)
  - Judicial system, University of Michigan, newsclippings 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Law Library dedication 1981 (Box 1)
  - Law School 1969 (Box 1)
  - Law School capital campaign 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Law School capital campaign 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Major gifts 1973-1976 (Box 2)
  - Medical School 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Open meetings of Board of Regents 1969-1972 (Box 2)
  - Open meeting law and right to privacy laws 1979 (Box 2)
  - Out-of-state tuition problems 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Outside employment of faculty 1971 (Box 2)
  - Permanent Alumni Center Committee 1977 (Box 2)
  - Physical Therapy Program, discontinuance 1981 (Box 2)
  - PIRGIM (Public Interest Research Group in Michigan)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1977 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
  - Population Planning Department, discontinuance 1977 (Box 2)
  - Power Center for the Performing Arts 1969-1971 (Box 2)
  - Presidents Club 1971-1976 (Box 2)
  - Regents
    - Annual reports 1973-1974, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1974-1980 (Box 2)
    - News clippings
      - 1969-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - Residential College 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Salary disclosure 1973 (Box 2)
  - School of Education 1969 (Box 2)
  - Shady Trails camp 1970 (Box 2)
  - South Africa divestiture 1977-1979, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - South Africa divestiture, news clippings 1979 (Box 3)
  - State Board of Education/School of Osteopathy 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Student discipline 1970, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Student housing 1969-1979 (Box 3)
  - Student members of Board of Regents 1972 (Box 3)
  - Tuition increase 1970 (Box 3)
  - Undergraduate admissions, report to Regents 1974 (Box 3)
- Board of Regents Correspondence
  The Board of Regents Correspondence files are arranged chronologically and cover many of the same subjects as the topical files. These files include Nederlander's personal correspondence relating to the Board of Regents and the University of Michigan, as well as materials distributed to all members of the Board of Regents. In addition, both these files and the Topical Files contain a significant amount of correspondence received from students and parents, stating their opinions on various university issues, such as the divestiture of its investments in South Africa. Some gaps exist in the Correspondence files; there are no files for 1971, or 1973 through 1976.
  - November 1968-March 1969, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - April-December 1969, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - 1970, 14 folders (Box 3)
  - 1970, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1972, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1977, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - 1978, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - January-August 1979, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - August-December 1979 (Box 5)
  - 1980, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - 1981, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - 1982, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - 1983, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - 1984, 2 folders (Box 5)